尼尔·阿姆斯特朗在月球上说下了那句著名的话
The fateful first steps of Neil Armstrong on to the lunar surface and his immortal words,
“这是我的一小步 是人类的一大步”
"That's One small step for man, one giant leap for mankind"
这个画面向全世界约6亿观众以现场直播的形式播出
was broadcast to a worldwide audience of about 600 million.
但早前人们对于该不该直播心里完全没底
And yet it was touch and go as to whether it would be broadcast live at all.
NASA一些人认为直播这种事情没什么科学意义
Some at NASA thought that it was not scientifically important,
没它任务也能正常进行下去
the mission would work perfectly well without it.
还浪费重量 浪费电能 浪费传输带宽
And therefore would be a waste of weight, power and transmission bandwidth,
更不用说把信号传回地球这种高难操作了
not to mention the challenge of getting the signals back to the Earth.
幸运的是 NASA的另一些人意识到了直播将是一次绝好的公关机会
Luckily some people in NASA were more switched on to the fact that a broadcast like this
would be a worldwide PR goldmine.
还能让为之买单的美国纳税人看到他们的钱都花在哪了
And also allowing the US tax payers who were footing the bill to see where their money was going.
NASA中比较开明的人之一是阿波罗11号登月舱指令长尼尔·阿姆斯特朗
One of those more enlightened at NASA was the commander of the lunar module for Apollo 11, Neil Armstrong.
身为指令长 他有权在最后一刻决定登陆的时候要不要直播
And as the commander, he would have the final say
if a live TV camera would or would not be used on the landing,
而之后的画面 就是历史了
the rest they say, is history.
但同不同意直播是一回事
But agreeing to use a live TV camera is one thing,
把直播信号传回地球就是另一回事了
getting it to broadcast live a signal back earth is another.
本期视频将给大家介绍阿波罗任务中使用的直播摄像机
This is the story of the live TV camera's that were used on the Apollo missions.
在今天这个几乎每个智能手机、平板和笔记本都有微型高清摄像头的时代
In this day and age of
tiny high definition video camera's in virtually every smartphone, tablet, and laptop,
有时很难相信在20世纪60年代阿波罗计划的时候
it's sometimes hard to believe but at the time of Apollo in the 1960's,
电视摄像机是又大又笨重又耗电的设备
TV camera's were big bulky power-hungry devices
通常只出现在电视台演播室 还要配合气动或液压底座上
usually reserved for TV studios that were wheeled around on pneumatic or hydraulic pedestals,
还没有电气控制的支架 摄像机也都是真空管的
and that's without the racks support electronics all using vacuum tubes.
NASA曾使用胶片相机来拍摄大家所见的高质量的任务片段
NASA had used film cameras to get the high-quality footage we see of the missions,
但这要等到任务结束后 胶片送回地球冲洗后才能看到
but that wasn't available until after the mission was over
and the film had been returned to earth and developed.
而电视将提供发生在38.4万公里外的太空中发生的几乎实时的画面
Television on the other hand, would give a nearly real-time view of what was happening in space,
or 384,000 km away from the moon.
但是做一个足够小、足够轻、功耗足够低的电视摄像机太难了
But getting a TV camera small enough, light enough
and with very low power consumption was going to be a difficult,
尤其考虑到NASA要让摄像机能配合登月舱使用而设定的规格限制
especially considering the NASA specification it had to work with for the Lunar lander.
还会造成一场技术大战
This would also create a technology fight
决定谁家的系统能用于从月球上进行电视直播
as to whose system would be used to get live TV from the moon.
相机的重量不超过6磅/2.7公斤，功率不超过7瓦
The camera had to weigh no more than 6lb or 2.7kg and consume no more than 7 watts power,
这与我们今天的标准USB手机充电器差不多
that's about the same as a standard USB phone charger we have today.
就是那种需要几个小时才能给你的手机充电的慢速充电器
You know, the slow ones that take hours to recharge your phone.
而摄像机还要在航天器外的真空空间和航天器内部使用
Because it would be used outside the spacecraft in the vacuum of space as well as inside,
所以它们必须能承受阴暗处-157摄氏度到阳光下的+127摄氏度的温度波动
they had to withstand a temperature swing from -157 C in the shade to + 127 C in the sunlight,
这种剧烈温度变化只需进入和离开航天器的阴影就可以在几秒钟内发生
something that could happen in seconds just by going into and out of the shadow of the spacecraft.
最后的困难是信号传输
The final hurdle was the transmission.
虽然NASA有足够带宽从指令舱 登月舱发送完整的4-5MHz 525/60 NTSC视频
Although NASA had enough bandwidth to send nearly full 4-5MHz 525/60 NTSC video back
from both the command module and the lunar lander,
但画面信号还必须与数据、遥测和语音通信共享带宽
they also had to share it with data, telemetry and voice communications.
为了保证从月球上用小天线发射时有一个良好的信噪比
To assure a good signal to noise ratio when transmitting from the moon with a small antenna
并为各种未知事件留好余量
and a host of other unknowns as this had never been done before,
留给画面信号带宽只有500kHz/0.5MHz
they limited it to just 500khz or 0.5 Mhz.
这样的带宽完全塞不下525行30帧的标准电视信号
There was simply no way you could have the 525 lines at 30 frames per second of normal TV with that bandwidth.
但是可以传320行 10帧的逐行扫描画面
However, they could just about do it if they used just 10 frames per second
and 320 lines with no interlacing.
这是一种非标准的慢速扫描格式
This was a none standard slow-scan format
在发送至全世界的电视之前需要进行转换
that would need to be converted before it could be sent out to the worlds' TV.
格式对于快速移动的图像来说 效果也不好
And would not work well with fast-moving images.
但他们感觉在太空或月球上的宇航员之类肯定不会移动得很快
But they figured that subjects like the astronauts in space or on the moon
所以这样的帧数倒也无妨
wouldn't be moving very fast anyway, so that would be acceptable.
他们还试过一套数字传输系统 但该系统用的是20MHz的带宽
A digital transmission system was also tried but that used 20MHz of bandwidth
那年代又没有够好的压缩算法 更没有够快的计算机 就没用上
because at the time there were no compression algorithms or computers fast enough to use them,
even if they existed.
在阿波罗计划中 NASA与美国无线电公司(RCA)签订合同 为指令舱制造摄像机
For the Apollo program, NASA contracted RCA to make a camera for the Command module,
与西屋电气签订合同 为登月舱制造摄像机
and Westinghouse to make one for the Lunar lander.
虽然西屋电气家的炊具、冰箱和电视等产品挺有名的
Although Westinghouse was better known for things like cookers, fridges and TV's,
但他们其实也为军方生产耐用电子设备
they also made hardened electronic equipment for the Military
包括用于船舶和直升机的小型单色电视摄像机
including small monochrome TV camera's for ships and helicopters.
他们也是最早自主研发定制集成电路的公司之一
They were also one of the first companies to make their own custom integrated circuits.
RCA摄像机是第一个开发并用于阿波罗7号任务的摄像机
The RCA camera was the first to be developed and used on Apollo 7 mission
并用于之后除阿波罗9号之外的所有任务
and then every mission apart from Apollo 9.
左侧为转换后的国家广播电视画面 右侧为阿波罗7号上拍摄的转换前的画面
最初的几次传输画面是黑白的
The first few transmissions were in black and white,
尽管从摄像机直出的信号图像质量并不太糟
and although the image quality directly from the camera signal
但这个信号是和广播用的信号分开的
which was recorded separately to the signal which went out the broadcast wasn't too bad.
且当时还要把信号转换为525行30帧的电视信号
By the time it had been converted up to the 525 line 30 fps,
再通过模拟信号链路经由卫星转发给全球
and sent over analogue transmission lines and satellite links for domestic broadcast,
画质已经降低非常多了
the picture quality had degraded quite a lot.
这突出了在当时的另一个问题
This would highlight another issue, in that at the time,
就是电视信号格式的转换是非常原始的
the methods for conversion from one TV format to another were very basic.
NASA将慢速扫描信号转换为广播格式的最初过程
The initial process which NASA used to convert the slow scan signal to broadcast format
就是把正常制式的摄像机对着播放来自阿波罗的慢速扫描信号的电视
was simply to point a normal studio TV camera at the screen showing the Slowscan images from Apollo.
然后播出去
And then rebroadcast that.
在后来的任务中 才换成专用的RCA扫描转换机
On later missions, this was changed to a dedicated RCA scan converter.
登月舱上拍摄登月过程的摄像机是由西屋电气制造的
The camera for the lunar module and moon landings was built by Westinghouse
他们利用其军工领域的技术经验研发了这样一款摄像机
who used their military knowledge and experience to create a camera
性能远远超当时现有的传统正析摄像管和光导摄像管
that was far more capable than any existing conventional image orthicons and vidicons tubes.
他们使用的是次级电子导电摄像管(SEC)
The type of camera tube they used was Secondary Electron Conduction or SEC tube.
简单来讲就是一个光电倍增器或图像增强器
Basically, this was a photomultiplier or image intensifier.
有很好的动态范围
It had excellent dynamic range,
能够同时看到非常明亮和非常黑暗的物体而不会使图像曝光过度
that's the ability to view both very bright and very dark objects
at the same time without overexposing the image,
是月球上非常明亮场景下的理想选择
ideal for the very bright conditions on the moon.
传感器本身也非常敏感 可以用在非常暗光的场景下
It was also very sensitive and could see in very low light conditions.
唯一的问题是 摄像机在任何情况下都不能直接对着太阳
The only problem with this was that it could not be pointed directly at the sun
即使关机也不行
even when it was turned off.
否则会马上烧毁摄像管的传感器
If it was it would instantly destroy the tube sensor.
还有一个问题是该摄像管使用的是8千伏的电源
There was also the problem in that the tube used an 8kV supply.
在太空的真空中 这种高电压可能会泄漏并产生电弧
In the vacuum of space this high voltage could leak and create an electric arc,
而且在太空 电弧还看不见 因为我们看到的电弧是空气分解产生的等离子体
though it would be invisible because the arcing we see is the plasma created by the breakdown of the air.
因此为了避免这种情况 必须使用新的特殊合金来制作电气触点
So new special alloys had to be used for the electrical contacts to avoid this.
在阿波罗11号上 摄像机被固定在模块化设备贮藏组件中
On Apollo 11, the camera was fixed in the Modularized Equipment Stowage Assembly
组件会在登月舱着陆后展开
which was deployed when the lander had touched down.
从而让全世界在电视直播中看到阿姆斯特朗走下梯子讲那句经典台词
This was set up to allow the shot of Armstrong
stepping off the ladder, and uttering his immortal words to be seen by the world on live TV.
然后宇航员拿起摄像机 放在登月舱旁边的三脚架上
The camera was then picked up and placed on a tripod away from the lander
这样就可以显示宇航员的活动与放置国旗的画面
so that it could show the astronauts moving around and placing the flag.
当时还没发拍摄宇航员离开月球的画面
There was no way to show the departure from the moon,
因为摄像机是通过电缆连接到登月舱上的
because the camera was connected to the lander by a cable,
而天线安装在登月舱上升段 起飞后分离 信号就断了
and the antenna was on the ascent stage which cut the connection to the camera at lift off.
直到后来阿波罗15号带去了月球车 上面自带传输天线
It wasn't until Apollo 15 and the lunar rover which had its own transmission antenna
才能在现场直播中看到宇航员从月球起飞的跟拍画面
could the departure be seen and followed on a live broadcast.
60年代初至中期 还只有少数人买得起彩色电视
In the early to mid 60s, color TV was still limited to the few people who could afford them
也没几个电视台演彩色信号
and the few stations that broadcast color transmissions.
因此当时并没有考虑让阿波罗给地球传回彩色电视信号
So there wasn't much thought put into broadcasting a color signal from Apollo back to earth.
但到了1969年阿波罗10号时 彩色电视已经非常普及了
But by the time of Apollo 10, in 1969, color TV was much more widespread.
但演播室的摄像机仍然又大又重
But the studio cameras were still large and heavy,
使用3或4个摄像管 红、绿、蓝三种颜色各一个
using 3 or 4 camera tubes, one for each color of red, green and blue,
仍然太大 无法在航天器上使用
still far too large to be used in a spacecraft.
西屋电气开发了一套彩色摄像系统 可以安装在现有的单色摄像管上
Westinghouse developed a color system that could be fitted to it's existing monochrome camera tube
使用的是CBS工程师Peter Goldmark博士在40年代提出的一个想法
using an idea which had been developed in the 1940s by CBS engineer Dr. Peter Goldmark,
CBS和西屋电气为此还发生了冲突
something which CBS and Westinghouse clashed over,
Goldmark和CBS声称彩色系统和摄像机都是他们的功劳
with Goldmark & CBS claiming credit for color system and camera,
但西屋电气其实只用了色轮部分
even though Westinghouse only used the color wheel,
其余的都是他们自己的、Goldmark时代还没有的电子器件设计
the rest was their own design using electronics
which were not available when Goldmark developed his version.
这个同步色轮有特殊形状的红、蓝、绿滤光片
This synchronized color wheel had specially shaped red, blue and green filters
经过CBS的工程师的调整 有了各自正确的进光量
which were advised by the CBS engineers to allow the correct amount of light in.
色轮以精确的速度在摄像管前旋转
It spun in front of the camera tube at precisely the correct speed
产生一连串的红、蓝、绿场
to create a sequence of red, blue and green fields,
以相同的顺序重新组合后 就能在接收端重新显示高质量的彩色图像
which when combined in the same order, recreated a good quality color picture at the receiving end.
以此研发出了一款相对简单、轻量、低功率的摄像机
This would create a relatively simple to use, lightweight, low power camera,
非常适合在太空和月球上使用
ideal for use in space and on the moon.
所用的非标准405行/144场的制式也不是问题
The non-standard 405 lines/ 144 field sequential color format wasn't a problem either
因为NASA收到的格式都不是标准的 在播出之前都需要转换
because none of the NASA formats was standard, and would still need converting before they could be broadcast.
CBS实验室还创建了一个基于磁盘驱动器的视频转换器
CBS Labs also create a magnetic disk drive-based video converter
将场序图像转换成标准NTSC彩色电视信号
to to turn the field sequential images in to a standard NTSC color TV signal.
虽然西屋公司在阿波罗11号飞行前就已向NASA展示了他们的彩色摄像机
Although Westinghouse had shown their color camera to NASA before Apollo 11 flight,
但在第一次登月时已经太晚了
it was too late to get it on the first moon landing,
所以全世界只看到了黑白的直播画面
so the world saw the live footage in Black and & White only.
第一次彩色直播用在阿波罗12号上
The first live color broadcast occurred on Apollo 12,
尽管对摄像机来说事情并不顺利
though things didn't go too well for the camera.
宇航员艾伦·宾在将摄像机从登月舱中搬出时
The camera was accidentally pointed at the sun by Astronaut Alan Bean
不小心将摄像机对准了太阳 瞬间烧了SEC管
as he carried it from the Lunar Module which instantly destroyed the SEC tube,
当场下播
terminating the live broadcast.
虽然阿波罗11号的画质因转换过程和多个广播中继而有所下降
Although the picture quality on Apollo 11 was degraded due to the conversion process
and multiple broadcast steps,
但阿姆斯特朗和奥尔德林在月球上的幽灵般的图像
the ghostly images of Armstrong and Aldrin on the moon
似乎与公众想象中的月球的另类形象一拍即合
seemed to match the otherworldly image of the moon in the public eye.
有人说如果传送的是演播室的高质量画面
Some said that if it had been in studio quality,
似乎不如公众看到的远古门锁画质更可信
it would have seemed less believable than the rather lo-fi monochrome version the public saw.
除了在接收站工作的技术人员之外
Few people outside of the technicians working at the receiving stations
很少有人看到直接来自阿波罗的原始慢速扫描电视信号
saw the raw Slow scan TV signal directly from Apollo.
这些是最高质量视频版本 直接记录在模拟遥测数据磁带上
These were the highest quality versions and recorded directly to analogue telemetry data tapes,
因为后续信号都被转换为NTSC制式 以便向全世界广播
as the signal was being converted to NTSC for broadcast around the world.
然而 在某段时间 据说是在20世纪80年代
However, at some point, it was believed in the 1980s,
它们被复写掉并重新用于NASA的陆地卫星计划 因为当时录像带严重短缺
they were erased and reused for NASA's Landsat program, which was facing severe tape shortage at the time.
又由于低质量的广播版本在世界各地被广泛复制
Because the lower quality broadcast versions were widely copied around the world,
没有人想过要录制质量更高的慢速扫描电视画面原件
no one thought much about the recordings of the higher quality Slow scan TV originals
直到很久以后 人们开始寻找原件才意识到这些
until much later, when people started looking for them,
不少阴谋论也因此冒了出来
something which has fueled many a conspiracy theory since.
RCA公司从一开始就想参与登月活动
RCA wanted to be involved on the moon landings from the beginning,
为美国广播公司向后兼容彩色电视标准
backwardly compatible color TV standards for the US broadcasters,
对NASA选择了西屋电气很不满
and were rather upset that NASA chose Westinghouse,
更为NASA选择了与RCA系统不兼容的连续彩色摄像机不满
and a sequential color camera that was not compatible with the RCA system.
RCA的老板不想使用连续的彩色系统
The boss of RCA didn't want to use the sequential color system
所以在阿波罗15号之前都没参与竞争
which kept them out of the running until Apollo 15
并在最后为月球车制造了一个连续彩色摄像机
when they eventually did make a sequential color camera for the lunar rover.
尽管西屋公司最终失去了与RCA公司签订的彩色摄像机合同
Although Westinghouse eventually lost the contract to RCA for the color cameras,
但地球上看到的RCA月球车摄像机部署画面
when the deployment of RCA lunar rover camera was shown back on earth,
则都是由西屋电气摄像机拍的
it was done with a Westinghouse camera.
最后 Peter Goldmark博士看到基于自己在40年代成果而开发的摄像机
In the end, Dr. Peter Goldmark was very pleased when the first color images were sent back from Apollo
从阿波罗发回第一张彩色图像时也非常高兴
using a camera based on the same principles he had developed back in the 1940s.
感谢观看~
So I hope you liked the video and if you did then please, thumbs up, click the bell notification, subscribe and share and don't forget Patreon supporters get ad-free versions before they go public on Youtube.